<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Bride's Church, Dublin, April 17. 1698. Upon occasion of a resolution taken in this city, of putting the laws in execution against vice and immoralities / by Pet. Browne.</title>
            <author>Browne, Peter, ca. 1666-1735.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64551000</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64551000</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08579)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2863:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Bride's Church, Dublin, April 17. 1698. Upon occasion of a resolution taken in this city, of putting the laws in execution against vice and immoralities / by Pet. Browne.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Peter, ca. 1666-1735.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray and are to be sold at his shop in Skinner-Row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVIII. [1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers, XXV, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>Bride</hi>'s Church, <hi>Dublin, April</hi> 17. 1698.</p>
            <p>Upon Occaſion of a RESOLUTION Taken in This City, Of Putting The Laws in Execution AGAINST <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Immoralities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> PET. BROWNE, B D. <hi>Sen. Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of</hi> Trin. Col. DUBLIN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed by <hi>Joſeph Ray,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop in <hi>Skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-Row</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:184395:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184395:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:184395:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reader is deſired to take Notice, That the Third Head was Omitted in the Speaking, and part of the Second for Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. And that the Sentences under the Second Head in an Italick Character, are Mr.</hi> Boyſe'<hi>s, in his Sermon Dedicated to the</hi> SOCIETIES FOR REFORMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184395:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>NUMBERS XXV. 11.</bibl>
               <q>Phinehas the Son of Eleazer, the Son of Aaron the Prieſt, hath turned my Wrath away from the Children of Iſrael (while he was Zealous for my ſake among them) that I Conſumed not the Children of Iſrael in my Jealouſie.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> came to their laſt Station in order to paſs over <hi>Jordan,</hi> the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Countries were terrified with their Numbers; and therefore the King of <hi>Moab</hi> combin'd with the <hi>Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> againſt them. And, as was very uſual with moſt Heathen Princes upon the like Occaſions he ſends for <hi>Balaam</hi> a Man famous for Divinations, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult about the Event, and Encourage his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184395:4"/> People with a Promiſe and Aſſurance of Succeſs. But by the Order and Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of GOD, he propheſies quite the contrary, and fore-tells the Deſtruction of <hi>Moab,</hi> and the Neighbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries by the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> for which he was ſent home with Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>But thô he could not ſpeak any thing to the King but what GOD had put in his Mouth, yet his Affection for the <hi>Midianites</hi> (who were probably his Country-men, becauſe we read he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd home, and afterwards was Kill'd among them) made him give their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the only Advice which cou'd poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly injure the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and that was, To ſend many of their Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into the Camp, which by their Beauty and Allurements might entice the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> firſt to Unlawful Marriages and Whoredom, and then to prophane the Name and Worſhip of GOD by their Idolatry. And accordingly the Wile took, and as we read in the firſt Verſe of this Chapter, <hi>The Men began to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Whoredom with the Daughters of Moab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this, GOD ſent a Plague among them; and <hi>Moſes</hi> by his Command,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184395:4"/> gave poſitive Orders throughout the Camp to all the Governours and Leaders, that they ſhou'd put to death all thoſe who were guilty of theſe Crimes. But as appears from the manner of the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Number and Quality of thoſe who fell in League with the Heathen Women was ſo great, that Execution was delay'd; ſo that they out-brav'd the Laws, and ſtruck a Terror into all thoſe who were well affected, and had refrain'd from thoſe lewd Practices. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that <hi>Zimri,</hi> a Perſon of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among them, in open Contempt of the Laws and Magiſtrates, brought a <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> Woman along with him <hi>in the ſight of all the Congregation. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas</hi> ſeeing this, follows them into the Tent, and kills them both in the very Act of Fornication: Then the Plague was ſtay'd, and this Action of <hi>Phine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>has</hi> ſaid to be the Cauſe of it, <hi>For Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas the Son</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Being at this Time to diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe Perſons, who have bravely ſet themſelves to give Vice and Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities an open profeſs'd Oppoſition in this City, and to ſtem that current of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs which threatned to over-whelm us; I have made choice of theſe words,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184395:5"/> that I might propoſe to you this Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Pattern of Zeal; that you might ſee how this was commendable in him, and how far it is imitable by you. And that I might lay before you thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things which in this Text are ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, as well for your Direction and more Prudent Management, as for your Encouragement in that Worthy Deſign of yours; which if rightly manag'd, muſt be very pleaſing and acceptable to GOD and all good Chriſtians. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">I. The firſt thing obſervable from theſe words is, That Perſons even in a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Capacity, may and ought to ſhew their Zeal for GOD againſt open and bare-fac'd Impiety. For tho' <hi>Phinehas</hi> was the High-Prieſts Son, yet we read of no Place nor Power that he had, till he was afterwards employ'd as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander againſt the <hi>Midianites.</hi> So that this Action was not proper either to his Place or Quality, but as he was an <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elite;</hi> and he had the Execution of the Laws in his Power no otherwiſe, than by vertue of that General Command at the 5th Verſe, which was common to others as well as him. And accordingly thô <hi>Moſes</hi> mention only <hi>Phinehas,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184395:5"/> the firſt that led the way; and <hi>Zimri</hi> as being a Perſon of the greateſt Quality of thoſe that were ſlain: yet <hi>Joſephus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating this Paſſage ſays, That a great number of other young Men being Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by this couragious Action, took heart, and roſe up in open Oppoſition to the Tranſgreſſors, and Executed the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Moſes</hi> upon them all.</p>
            <p>But tho' this Command was General, yet there was this Peculiar in that Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Phinehas,</hi> that the Command be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing directed to the Judges and Leaders <hi>to deſtroy every one their Men</hi> (i. e.) to puniſh thoſe under their Juriſdiction <hi>Zimri</hi> being Head of a chief Houſe among them, and therefore not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately under the Power of others, thought to carry it with a high Hand; to practice his Wickedneſs openly him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by that means to encourage it in others. But <hi>Phineas</hi> being acted with a Zeal for GOD and the Command of <hi>Moſes,</hi> undertook the Exploit, and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted that Sentence upon him, which he neglected to Execute upon others.</p>
            <p>Now this gave occaſion to the Sect of the Zealots among the Jews, whoſe Power was for a long time very ſacred
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184395:6"/> among them; and they had a right to execute the Sentence of the Law upon any Perſon they apprehended in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of Blaſpheming, or Prophaning the Temple <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was all built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a tradition they held from <hi>Moſes</hi> grounded as they conjectur'd, upon this action of <hi>Phineas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we have ſome inſtances in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of particular perſons, who upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary occaſions have by a Zeal inflam'd and a mighty Impuls upon their Spirits, become the Executioners of God's immediate Vengeance upon Bold and Scandalous Sinners. As particularly that of <hi>Elias</hi> deſtroying all the Prophets of <hi>Baal;</hi> and <hi>Matathias</hi> ſlaying the Jew that offered Incenſe upon a Heathen Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. And that action of our Saviours twice repeated, of driving the Buyers and Sellers out of the Temple, thô he did it by the priviledge of his Kingly Power; yet he was ſuppos'd by the Jews to do it upon this principle of Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotiſm: For otherwiſe they had a fair Accuſation againſt him for a Riotous and Illegal Aſſault; and being but a private Perſon taking upon him the Office of a Magiſtrate.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:184395:6"/>
            <p>Now this fiery temper of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lots was very commendable, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times neceſſary under the Law; yet it is not practicable in that degree under the tender and merciful Spirit of the Goſpel. For then their Obedience was external, and therefore required ſutable Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this life; But now the inward purity of our Souls is requir'd, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can make Men afraid of ſinning in their Minds but a clear revelation of Hell, and a full proſpect of eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore theſe are the only ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Lord now. In the firſt times of the Goſpel indeed, death was inflicted upon malicious obſtinate Offenders by a ſupernatural power; but this, with all the other acts of God's extraordinary diſpenſations have ceaſed, ſo that all ſuch mighty impulſes pretended now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days are only from the Devil.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel propoſes no temporal Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for the ſins of Men, but ſuch as follow the nature of the Sins them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And therefore the ſevereſt Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Cenſures are the Expoſing Men to ſhame, and Cutting them off from the Body of the Church, and ſo conſigning them over unto the judgment of the Great Day.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184395:7"/> But thô it be now utterly unlawful in us to puniſh Vice in others, unleſs where we have Authority our ſelves, or derive it from the Laws of the Land: Yet thus much is very evident from this action of <hi>Phineas,</hi> and thoſe other inſtances of Zeal conſequent to it; that all Men may, and ought to ſhew their Zeal for the glory of God, and diſcouragment of Vice, by all thoſe means which are permitted by the Goſpel. And there are ſeveral ways of doing this, As by ſhewing our diſlike to it at all times, and in all perſons; by reproving the ſins of others whenever it is proper and ſeaſonable, and that we have any hopes our Reproofs will do good; and laſtly by doing all that in us lies, to promote the Execution of thoſe good and wholſom Laws which are Enacted againſt impudent Profaneſs and Impiety.</p>
            <p>And that which makes this laſt way of ſhewing our Zeal ſo neceſſary now, is becauſe multitudes who go by the name of Chriſtians, have caſt off all fear of any thing elſe but Temporal Laws; all the Methods of the Church againſt ſuch Scandalous Offenders have quite loſt their force.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:184395:7"/>
            <p>There was a time, and O! that we might ſee it in our days, when Men knew the ſtrength of Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; when they were ſenſible that God was with his Church in all its Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciary Proceedings, ratifying all its juſt Sentences, binding of them in Heaven, and recording of them there to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd at the great Day of Accounts. But now they regard nothing but what they feel, ſo that there is no way left of dealing with them, but by thoſe Human Laws which they dread more than Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and the Power of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, which they fear more then that God who is a Conſuming Fire.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond thing I ſhall obſerve from theſe words is, That the nature of a true Zeal conſiſts in our Indignation at what is plainly againſt the Laws of God, and evidently ſinful. That inſtance we have of a true Zeal here was againſt Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Fornication, and the Idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>Baal Pehor;</hi> which as one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves from the ſignification of the name, was an Idol purpoſely contrived to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite People to Lewdneſs and Impurity by the ſight of it: and therefore his Zeal was approved by God in theſe words,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184395:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:184395:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:184395:9"/> 
               <hi>while he was zealous for my ſake among them.</hi> This of being incens'd at the known and <hi>unconteſted</hi> ſins of Men is the being truly zealous for the ſake of God; and not when People are tranſported a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt things dubious, and of no great moment; when they lay out all their Zeal againſt Circumſtances, and things in their own nature lawful or indifferent. There is more requir'd in order to a true Zeal than meer heat of our Blood, and a great indignation of mind: People may be thus far zealous in a bad, as well as a good Cauſe; For the Midianites were no doubt very zealous againſt the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, when they proſtituted their Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of greateſt Quality to deſtroy them. So that being levell'd at things which are plainly againſt the Laws of God, is the only diſtinguiſhing mark of a true Zeal. And it is more or leſs true accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the evidence and plaineſs of thoſe Precepts of God againſt which the ſins are committed. When the things againſt which we are zealous are dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, our Zeal if violent is blamable; if the things are of no great moment or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, then our Zeal is trifling and frivolous; if the things are in their own nature lawful, then our Zeal is downright ſinful.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:184395:9"/>
            <p>Now Fornication and Adultery, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Swearing, Blaſphemy and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſs, Drunkenneſs and Gluttony, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Gain and Oppreſſion, Rebellion and Diſobedience to Laws and Government, Breaking of Amity among Chriſtians, and Diſſolving of Unity in the Worſhip of GOD; Theſe and ſuch-like are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and palpably againſt the expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of GOD: and therefore theſe are the things againſt which our Zeal ſhou'd be levell'd. For otherwiſe we have juſt cauſe to ſuſpect that it proceeds from Natural Temper, or Humor, or Intereſt, or Ignorance and Miſtake, or from the Deluſions of the Devil, and our own Imaginations: But in things of that groſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nature, our Zeal is always Safe and Commendable.</p>
            <p>And therefore here, by the way, I ought not to omit the Juſt Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the late Zeal of our Diſſenting Brethren, in their hearty Endeavours, and liberal Contributions for carrying on this Deſign of putting the Laws in Execution againſt ſuch of thoſe Vices as are made liable to Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Had they begun this Work, no one could have ſaid, <hi>That it was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184395:10"/> Deſign of a Party,</hi> but a True and Regular Zeal; becauſe the Inſtances are ſuch as are plainly and directly againſt the Laws of GOD, as well as thoſe of the Land; and not ſuch as are Dubious and Indifferent in their own nature: No, we commend them for their hearty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence with us, and we hope not to be out-done by them in this good Work.</p>
            <p>But ſince all this viſible Piety, and Zeal againſt Irreligion and Profaneſs, hath firſt appear'd <hi>among the Members of the Eſtabliſh'd Church,</hi> it muſt be Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that our Conſtitution and Principles are better Calculated for the Encouragement of all Vertue and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Suppreſſion of Vice among them; and nothing can poſſibly be a greater Inducement to all well-diſpoſed People to joyn in its Communion, than to ſee what a Natural Tendency it hath to make People truly Good and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous.</p>
            <p>We muſt both of us with Sorrow of Heart confeſs, That our Separate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions have been the immediate Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Cauſe of all that <hi>Torrent of Profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Irreligion, Immorality and Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184395:10"/> which during the two late Reigns came in upon theſe Lands with an Irreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able violence;</hi> which hath ſo broke the Sinews of all Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline, and depriv'd the Church of that Power Originally inherent in it by a Divine Right deriv'd from Chriſt himſelf; that we are both of us now forc'd to fly to Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Laws for the Suppreſſion of ſuch Sinners, who having no fear of GOD before their Eyes, muſt neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Church.</p>
            <p>And 'tis a Melancholly Conſideration, that the Incorporation of the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Civil State, by a Conſtitution of Government in it ſelf ſo Excellently Contriv'd, as to reſerve to the Apoſtles Succeſſors, all their Divine Right and Primitive Authority in Matters purely Eccleſiaſtical; and yet in a due Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to the Civil Magiſtrate; ſhou'd, by our Diviſions, be brought to this, that they ſhall now act rather as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the State, than as Governours of the Church. And that the Addition of Temporal Laws in a Kingdom of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which were deſign'd to give ſtrength to her Cenſures, ſhou'd by this means come to have a quite contrary Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to ſwallow them all up, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184395:11"/> them almoſt wholly into Civil Power: Inſomuch that ſhe hath only her Doctrine left for Ornament, but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of that Original Power of Defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf, and Excluding all Impudent Impiety, Profaneſs, and Irreligion out of the Fold of Chriſt. So that there were generally better Chriſtians in the Church, when it was among Infidels, than now that there are ſo many Infidels ſuffer'd to be profeſt and actual Members of the Church.</p>
            <p>We muſt both I ſay acknowledge that theſe open and ſcandalous Sins of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Chriſtians, are the diſmal Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of our Diviſions; and therefore that there is a heavy and unſupportable Load of Guilt, where-ever the juſt and true Cauſe of them lies: And that it will lie either on their ſide or ours, is ſo plain a Truth that we can neither of us avoid it. I am not now going to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute where, But it follows from hence, that it is matter of infinite Concern to each of us to be very well Aſſur'd, that it doth not lie at our Door. There is not any thing in the world that we ought to be better reſolv'd in; For if there be not ſuch a manifeſt violation of the known poſitive Laws of GOD requir'd amongſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184395:11"/> us, that they cannot communicate with us, without plainly tranſgreſſing of them; then all their Zeal for Purer Worſhip will never be accounted a Zeal for the ſake of GOD. And if the Conſtitution of our Church doth oblige them to the committal of one Sin contrary to the known poſitive Laws of God, and the <hi>Intereſt of Practical Holineſs,</hi> then we muſt take all that load of Guilt upon our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Sure I am on which ſide ſoever the Cauſe lies, that our Uniting in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and Celebration of the Sacraments, wou'd be the moſt effectual means of Suppreſſing all this inſolent and hardened Impiety; and nothing elſe can do it intirely and laſtingly. And ſince we are all United <hi>In the main Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Practical Holineſs,</hi> what then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains toward the perfecting our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, but that in all theſe things which do not relate to <hi>Practical Holineſs,</hi> we in all Humility ſubmit to the Wiſdom of our Superiors? Who as is confeſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire us to be guilty of nothing which is contrary to it. And therefore I hope all People are now convinced that they may joyn with us without committing a Sin: And if ſo, this Inference is very
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184395:12"/> plain, That it is a Sin not to joyn with us.</p>
            <p>And ſince we are ſo <hi>happily agreed in all thoſe things that are great and valuable,</hi> why ſhould we break Communion for thoſe that are not ſo? O! that GOD would put it into the Hearts of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren, to weigh theſe heavy Conſequences in the Ballance, againſt <hi>thoſe few ſmall Differences in Opinion or Practice for which we yet differ,</hi> that what remains might no way obſtruct our Joynt Communion, and hinder us any longer from going into the Houſe of GOD as Friends together. This wou'd ſtrike an Awe upon bold and hardened Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and then <hi>wou'd the Reformation of theſe Scandalous Vices</hi> we now ſet our ſelves againſt <hi>begin where our Corruption did before:</hi> And thus <hi>by becoming an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, we ſhou'd become a Flouriſhing and Happy People.</hi> GOD grant that our United Endeavours for the Proſecution of Vice and Wickedneſs, may be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Means of Uniting us, not only <hi>in our Affections to one another,</hi> but in the Publick Worſhip of GOD, and Celebration of his Sacraments; which is the Neceſſary Condition of that Unity which alone will render us
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184395:12"/> one Church and People in the ſight of GOD.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Third thing obſervable from this Paſſage is, That our Zeal for the cauſe of God in all inſtances what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſhould contain it ſelf within thoſe bounds preſcrib'd by himſelf. As it muſt be againſt things plainly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Laws of God, ſo the manner of expreſſing it muſt be agreeable to them too. <hi>Phinehas</hi> is not commended here becauſe he was too haſty to expect a legal Proceſs, for the Command was po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive that they ſhould not ſtay for it; but for the ſpeedy execution of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Law with the hazard of his life, and becauſe he took it upon him when no one elſe dar'd to do it. And therefore that muſt needs be a blind and prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Zeal which ſets up for reformation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Manners, or Diſcipline by methods unwarrantable, either by the Laws of God or Man. The Zealots among the Jews were very good and uſeful in their firſt original, and therefore in great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration while they kept within the juſt and preſcrib'd limits of the Law: But afterwards they became a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and pernicious Sect to the whole
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184395:13"/> polity of the Jews, they committed all manner of Villanies under pretence of Reformation, and put to death many of the chief and worthieſt men of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And therefore men can't be too cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in this point, for whenever our Zeal prompts us to act in oppoſition to any of the Laws of God, or the innocent Laws of Men, 'tis all madneſs and fury. Our Zeal may carry us beyond the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, but not contrary to any one of them: as in this action of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas,</hi> it was more than his duty to ſlay one of another Tribe, but it was how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever according to the expreſs Command, for otherwiſe it had been an act of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Our Zeal in many inſtances may prompt us to do more than God requires of us, but never to do any thing that he forbids, for this will be reforming the ſins of Men by others in our Selves.</p>
            <p>Now as to your obſervance of human Laws in the management of your Zeal againſt Offenders, I need ſay but little they are a Fence to themſelves, and they regard every Man hath to his own quiet and ſafety, will oblige him in prudence
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184395:13"/> not to come under the laſh of them, by taking any courſe of Fraud or Violence that is unwarrantable.</p>
            <p>But as to the Laws of GOD, the moſt effectual way of keeping within due Bounds in this Undertaking, is by a Preſervation of your <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt as to your <hi>Sincerity</hi> in this good Work, you muſt take care that you are prompted to it out of a true Concern for the Glory of GOD, and Veneration for his Laws; together with a Concern for the good of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, a tender Regard for the Souls of other Men, and the diſcharging of a good Conſcience in doing all that in you lies to the promoting of theſe Ends. If theſe be the Motives that ſpur you on to give inſolent Profaneſs and Impiety an open Oppoſition, 'tis a glorious En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize; and you may hope that GOD who hath begun this good Work by you, will bring it to a good Perfection. This of a pure Intention alone can Entitle you to the Bleſſing of GOD both here and hereafter; and 'tis a great Pity that any one ſhou'd be the Inſtrument of ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184395:14"/> ſubſtantial a good, and yet loſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſecondly, As to your <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> this is to be ſecur'd both in <hi>reſpect of your ſelves,</hi> and in your <hi>Deportment to others.</hi> As to the firſt, You muſt not value your ſelves upon this, as being more holy than other Men; for Zeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sins of other People, thô it be good and commendable, yet is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad Rule of judging of the degrees of Piety in our ſelves; and yet of all Vertues it hath the directeſt Tendency to raiſe Mens Opinions of their own Piety, and puff them up with Spiritual Pride. Therefore let the notice we take of the Sins of others, make us rather reflect upon our ſelves, who are Sinners as well as they, thô perhaps not in the ſame Inſtances, or in the ſame degrees. And the moſt effectual way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving an humble Senſe of our own Religion and Performances, is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves with the Law of GOD, and not with the Lives of other Men; then we ſhall ſee ſo many Defects in our ſelves, that we ſhall never be proud of not being as wicked as other Men are.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:184395:14"/>
            <p>As it reſpects <hi>Others,</hi> you muſt ſhew your Humility by Obedience and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Magiſtrates in all your Proceedings; and by paying all Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Reſpect to your Superiors, notwithſtanding your Evidence againſt them; by avoiding all Affectation of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity and Moroſeneſs, and never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting or expreſſing any indecent Paſſion againſt Peoples Perſons; for 'tis not them, but their Sins you proſecute. There is a manner of accuſing People which thô it want no Courage or Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, yet diſcovers Meekneſs and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; and then it becomes the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Zeal when it hath this Undaunted Reſolution, without any mixture of the Heat and Fire of our Temper.</p>
            <p>There is a way of Proſecuting the Sins of Others ſo as to convince even them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that 'tis from no Prejudice to their Perſons, but a Zeal for the Glory of GOD, and a tender Concern for the good of their Souls: And therefore whenever this End can be effected with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and that you have juſt ground to think that their Converſion can be wrought by Secret Admonition, you are not to expoſe them to Publick Diſgrace
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184395:15"/> and Puniſhment. And you are to have ſuch a tender Regard to the Reputation of others, that you accuſe not any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon groundleſs Reports, or meer Suſpicions; for the bringing an hundred guilty Perſons to Puniſhment, will not recompence the Injury done to one who is wrongfully accus'd.</p>
            <p>And in the zealous Proſecution of other Peoples Sins, you muſt ever have a juſt regard to the Preſervation of your own Innocence. Some Sins are of that infectious Quality they catch like the Plague, and eſpecially thoſe of Laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in Youth, where there is a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to be wrought upon: <hi>Can a Man take Fire in his Boſom, and not be burnt?</hi> ſays <hi>Solomon</hi> to this ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; to ſhew us the nature of this Temptation is ſuch, that there is no way of Safety, but by cutting off all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of it. So that to ſeek Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſinning your ſelf, for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of other People, is not ſafe; and to gain their Conſent to a Sin by any means of Allurement or Circumvention is not innocent; ſince this is a degree of Guilt in them, equal to Actual Sin. This will harden People in their Vices ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than work their Reformation; And
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184395:15"/> therefore leave all theſe Methods to thoſe Evil Spirits, the common Enemies of Mankind whoſe proper Quality it is, firſt to entice People into Sin, and then upbraid and accuſe them for it. This is the only Objection that is or can be made againſt your Endeavours: And if you take care to prevent this, you will remove all ſuſpicion from thoſe who are truly zealous againſt Vice, and forward to promote the Diſcouragement of it, by all fair means of Proſecution and Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            <p>And let all this be done by you as true Sons of the Church and Members of its Communion, and let no Opinion of your own Piety or Devout Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances among your Selves inſinuate any Diſeſteem of the ſervice of the Church, which is much more acceptable to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD. Therefore be exact in the obſervance of its Cuſtoms and Conſtita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, nor endeavour to be more Holy by reparing for more frequent, or purer Worſhip to thoſe Congregations which have Separated from Us. You of all People can't do this without being a contradiction to your ſelves; for to the great Credit not only of Chriſtianity but of the Eſtabliſh't Church, you have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184395:16"/> made it appear, that People may in all reſpects be as Vertuous and Holy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Boſom of the Church, as 'tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to be out of it: So that you have effectually cut off from your ſelves all pretence of Separation for ever; this makes it utterly needleſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without Excuſe.</p>
            <p>One thing more I would recommend to You under this Head, and that is, That in all your Deſigns for the promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Vertue and Holineſs, you never abound ſo much in your own ſenſe, as to decline the Advice and Concurrence of the Biſhop and your reſpective Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. If you have a true <hi>Zeal,</hi> this is the only effectual way to have it <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Knowledge:</hi> But without their Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and Conduct, you will run into Errors before you are aware; and one Error in things of this nature is preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of many more. The Zealots among the Jews by aſſuming to themſelves what did not belong to them, proceeded at laſt to Elect and Ordain the High-Prieſt, deſpiſing the Rules of Birth (ſays <hi>Joſepbus</hi>) by which they were to Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; putting in Illiterate and Obſcure Men, ſuch as were prepar'd with Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Superſtition enough to back
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184395:16"/> their Proceedings; For having once broke in upon the Office and Priviledges of the Prieſthood, they knew not where to ſtop.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Another thing contain'd in theſe words is, That the Suppreſſion of Open Scandalous Impiety, is the moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al means of diverting GOD's Judgments from a Nation. There ſeem'd here to be a full purpoſe of GOD utterly to conſume the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in his Jealouſie; and while the Number and Quality of thoſe who defil'd themſelves with the <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> Women hinder'd the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, the Plague took off Four and Twenty Thouſand of them. But the Zeal of this Excellent Perſon in putting it in Execution, ſtopt the Plague in the midſt of its Rage, and turn'd away the Wrath of GOD from the whole Congregation.</p>
            <p>Now the Reaſon why this Action was of ſo much Power and Efficacy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with GOD in all likelihood was, Either becauſe he was one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Quality of thoſe that were guilty, and therefore influenc'd many Others by his Example: Or elſe, which is not improbable, becauſe this Couragious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184395:17"/> Action of his in beginning the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gave occaſion to the reſt of the Youth to follow his Example, and clear the whole Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And without doubt this was the reaſon why <hi>Phinehas</hi> was afterwards ſent Commander of the Army againſt the <hi>Midianites,</hi> becauſe GOD was likelier to bleſs that Hand with Succeſs which had thus led the way, and ſignaliz'd it ſelf by ſuch an Act of Exemplary Juſtice.</p>
            <p>This ſame Method of GOD's Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by whole Nations, according to that viſible Appearance of Piety and Open Face of Religion that is among them, is very diſcernable in the whole Series of GODs Diſpenſations to the Jews. And if we could ſee the Secret Hand that manages all the Affairs of this World, we ſhould find this to be at the bottom of them all, as the main Spring by which all Nations and Governments, all Cities and Communities undergo that great variety of Changes and Revolutions.</p>
            <p>Now the Wiſdom and the Juſtice of GOD in this is very Accountable by us, notwithſtanding that the Good are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly involv'd in the ſame Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with the Wicked. For,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:184395:17"/>1. Since good and bad People, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Saviour's Similitude, grow together like the <hi>Tares and the Wheat,</hi> they muſt therefore undergo all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Changes of Weather in common, let the Cauſe be what it will; <hi>His Sun muſt ſhine, and his Rain deſcend upon both alike.</hi> So that He hath no other way of dealing with whole Communities, but by ſending Temporal Bleſſings or Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon all together. And that GOD might appear Juſt and True in all his Dealings by the Children of Men, the Cauſe of theſe things muſt be ſomething that is common to them both; and that can be only this general Appearance of Goodneſs, or open Permiſſion of Scandalous Vices. For Secret Piety and Sincerity is proper only to the Good, and Rewardable in another World: And therefore as the Eternal Welfare of Men hereafter depends upon their own Secret Piety, ſo the Proſperity of whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions proceeds from the Open Profeſſion of Religion and Morality. So that in great Strictneſs Men are in all ſenſes, the true Cauſe of all the Misfortunes that befal them either in this World, or the next.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:184395:18"/>
            <p>GOD hath no other way, I ſay, of Dealing with whole Nations and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Men now, ſo as to proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Exception, and preſerve his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes inviolable. But when theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Ties and Temporary Obligations which Unite Men into Bodies here ſhall be Diſſolv'd, and Mankind New Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del'd into two Great and Oppoſite Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties never to mix again; then there will be full ſcope for the Exerciſe of all the Goodneſs of GOD upon the one, and of his juſt Vengeance upon the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Judgments of GOD may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Juſtly come upon the Good for want of a Zealous Endeavour of Suppreſſing thoſe Scandalous Vices in others. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be truly Vertuous and Holy in themſelves, and yet be without a good meaſure of Indignation at Open Impiety and Lewdneſs; ſo that they deſerve to ſhare in the Conſequences of that Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they did not uſe their utmoſt Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſuppreſs. And accordingly no queſtion but the Plague ſwept away ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe who were not guilty of the Sin that caus'd it; and would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd many more even of thoſe that were innocent, if this ſpeedy Suppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184395:18"/> of thoſe Vices had not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it.</p>
            <p>Nay thô we ſhou'd ſuppoſe no want of Zeal in thoſe that are Innocent, yet there is no Injuſtice in their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Sins of others: Firſt, Becauſe there are no Temporal Judgments can befal them, but what are the due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their own Sins; and Secondly, Becauſe thô they were not, but that they ſuffered wrongfully; yet this may be deſign'd by GOD, in order to an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Recompence hereafter: Whereas if the Bad ſhould fail of a Reward in this Life, there is no room left for it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Reaſon why bare-fac'd Impiety and open Profaneſs have ſuch a Tendency to bring down Judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all in Common is, Becauſe they are a direct Affront and Challenging of GOD. Publick Scandalous Sins when they grow general become a National Quarrel with him; and therefore lay a ſort of Neceſſity upon GOD to vindicate his Honour, and viſit a Nation while it is ſuch, for thoſe bold and open Defiances of Heaven, ſince there can be no opportunity for this hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:184395:19"/>
            <p>Beſides, This of openly expreſſing the inward corruptneſs of Mens Souls ſeems to be accidental to the guilt, for 'tis no more than proclaiming and giving vent to what was hidden before; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can't conceive how it can have ſo direct an Influence upon Mens Future State. For their greateſt Miſery will then be the Natural Reſult of their inward De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation of Mind and Conſcience; and therefore the other ſeems neceſſarily to require ſome Puniſhment in this Life, thô the many Evil Conſequences of Scandalous Sins may hereafter be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht by a poſitive Act of Juſtice. And therefore 'tis thoſe Open Sins which are not to be conceal'd from the knowledge of Men, ſuch as Curſing, Swearing and Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for which a <hi>Land is ſaid to mourn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hypocricy, thô it is a baſe and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable thing, yet it ſeems to have ſome ſenſe of GOD and Goodneſs left, thô it prepoſterouſly Act contrary to them both. It is commendable in this, that <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>tis aſham'd of its own Deformity; and the wearing the Mask of Religion, is a tacite Acknowledgment they wou'd be ſincerely good, if this cou'd be had
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184395:19"/> with the ſame Eaſe: And it ſhews they wou'd hide their Wickedneſs from GOD too, as well as from Men if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. But open Debauchery, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Impiety renounces all the intrinſick worth of Religion; 'tis a direct Affront to Heaven, and a Daring of GOD: And therefore when he is thus Challenged, he is conſtrain'd to Puniſh for the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his Honour. But when on the contrary they appear outwardly to be Holy, the Honour of GOD is how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever preſerv'd and the dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences prevented. Thô they have nothing of true Religion at the heart, yet it ſhews ſome Veneration for Him and his Laws; which thô it be that of Slaves and Vaſſals and not of True Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet 'tis not left without a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence proper for it.</p>
            <p>A meer form of Godlineſs and empty pretence of Piety often meets with a ſuitable Recompence; ſo that what our Saviour ſays of particular Hypocrites is true of greater Bodies and Communities of them, <hi>That they have their Reward.</hi> A famous inſtance of this is not out of the Memory of ſome yet alive; a time when all ſolid Vertue, and moral Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty was drein'd from Chriſtianity, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184395:20"/> nothing left but the outſide of it; yet this was proof againſt all the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who had more of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but too little of the outward ſhew and profeſſion of it. This gave them ſuch Succeſs, that they overcame all Difficulties, till at laſt Hypocriſy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd the Throne, ador'd by all its Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries; and reign'd till the Varniſh came off the guilded Idol, and diſcovered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Clay and Rottenneſs all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>if they had Ears to hear,</hi> I wou'd ſpeak ſomthing to thoſe bold and reſolute Sinners who are the occaſion of all this Trouble and Charge; But they are ſo far <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> that none of the Terrors of God can touch them, and therefore I muſt leave them to other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods. I ſhall only mind them here (if ever they are diſpos'd to conſider it) that beſides the proper guilt of their own ſins, they will in the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be accountable for all thoſe Evils upon their Country, which have been the conſequences of their ſins in this life: and that thô they may eſcape the hand of Juſtice here, yet Damnation expects them, and they are only Repriev'd till the Judgment of the Great Day.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:184395:20"/>V. The laſt thing I ſhall obſerve from hence is, That as the Suppreſſion of Scandalous Wickedneſs diverts the Judgments of God from a People in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, ſo it brings down particular Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings on the Heads of thoſe which are the Inſtruments of it. For this action of <hi>Phinehas, Behold</hi> ſays GOD <hi>I give him my Covenant of Peace,</hi> by which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters underſtand Proſperity, and all Temporal Bleſſings: And beſides it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that GOD would give him the Covenant of an Everlaſting Prieſthood, (<hi>i. e.</hi>) confirm it in the ſame Line to him and his Poſterity. But <hi>Eli</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards forfeited the Prieſthood for the contrary reaſon, <hi>becauſe his Sons made themſelves vile and he reſtrained them not.</hi> A tenderneſs to his own Children made him diſregard the Publick Good, and prefer the Eaſe and Quiet of his Private Family before the Publick Welfare of the Church: Whereas <hi>Phinehas</hi> in all likelihood, ran a great hazard of his Life, ſince <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Perſons, One the <hi>Head of a Chief Houſe,</hi> and the Other a <hi>Prince's Daughter of Midian;</hi> and therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably there wanted not People to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour a Revenge. And the Succeſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184395:21"/> muſt have been very uncertain at a time when their general Lewdneſs, as appears by this action of <hi>Zimri</hi>'s, out-brav'd the Laws and Magiſtrates, and therefore as it is Pſal. 106. <hi>This was counted to him for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs thrô all Generations for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was a Rare and Admirable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a truly generous Zeal and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Spirit, than which nothing is more acceptable to Almighty God; becauſe it places Him and his Cauſe uppermoſt in our Minds, and makes all things ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to his Will: this is the greateſt indication of a ſincere love of God, and is truly the higheſt pitch of Virtue. Even the Heathens had a mighty ſence of the excellence of this concern for the common Good, as appears from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Brave and Generous Actions they did for their Superſtition. And the wiſe Athenian Lawgiver being ask'd <hi>Which was the moſt effectual means of preſerving Juſtice and Equity in a City?</hi> anſwered, <hi>That thoſe who receive no Injury by unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things, be equally incens'd as thoſe who ſuffer by them.</hi> And gave this as the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſign of the decay of any Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>when every one is eagerly bent upon their own welfare, without regard to any thing beyond themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:184395:21"/>
            <p>The Goſpel improves and encourages this Excellent Temper, and requires ſuch a diſpoſition of heart, and mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the good of one another in all its Members, as if they were but one Family; and teaches to prefer the glory of God, above all that is near and dear to us. The deſcription of our Saviour's Temper in the 69 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> is, <hi>That the Zeal of Gods Houſe had eaten him up</hi> (i. e.) the Zeal and Concern he had for the glory of GOD and his Church, even prey'd upon his Spirits.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It follows, <hi>And the Reproaches of them that reproached thee is fallen upon me</hi> (i. e.) I have as quick and feeling a ſenſe of any reproach or diſhonour done to Thee, as if it were done to my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Let therefore the ſame Spirit be in us, and let us lay to heart the daily Profanations of GOD's holy Name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, the open Reproaches of his Divine Truths, and the manifold Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of his Laws with a hardy Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Publick Defiance. And let us not be wanting to do all that in us lies for the Glory of GOD, and the Dignity of his Laws; at a time when we have ſo fair an Opportunity given us of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184395:22"/> our Zeal for GOD, our Indignation at the Vices and Immoralities of the Age, and to promote a General Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Life and Manners.</p>
            <p>Why Men ſhou'd not be as Zealous in the Execution of Laws made againſt Vice, as of thoſe that are made in favour of their Temporal Intereſts, is hard to tell, unleſs it be, that they love the World better than they do GOD. And why giving of Evidence in theſe Caſes ſhould be more condemn'd, than in any Caſe of Injuſtice done to our ſelves, I know not; there can be no Reaſon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but becauſe People are more Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their Worldly Concerns, than they are of the Glory of GOD. What were theſe good Laws made for? Nay, what have we a Religion for? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly not for meer ſhew and formality. therefore all who had any hand in making theſe Pious Laws, are bound to forward and promote the Execution of them, as they will defend us all from the Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Solemn National Hypocriſie. 'Tis a ſhame to ſee with what Fierceneſs and great Expence of Time and Money, Men will proſecute an Affront done to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and yet leave all thoſe Excellent Laws that are made againſt the Publick
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184395:22"/> Reproaches of GOD's holy Name and his Religion, to lie neglected and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon.</p>
            <p>GOD be prais'd there is now a Spirit of Zeal and Fervour, anſwerable to that of <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſtirr'd up among us, with the true Qualifications and Temper of the Goſpel; in oppoſition to that grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit of Irreligion and Infidelity which hath bid open Defiance to GOD and Goodneſs. If we Cheriſh and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage it, we may promiſe our ſelves the Victory in the End: For true Vertue is then only in danger when 'tis attack'd with Methods of Treachery, and 'tis never ſafer than when it hath declar'd open War with Vice. The conteſt is now with Mens Vices, and not with their Opinions; 'tis not the Intereſt of a Party, but the common Cauſe of Chriſtianity. And 'tis a Noble Enterprize, for by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving theſe Immoralities, we ſtrike at the very Root of <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> which is now grown a many-Headed Monſter, and improv'd into a ſtrange variety of Profane and Atheiſtical Principles; all which look one way, and agree to make a Body againſt all reveal'd Religion, and the Myſteries of the Goſpel. 'Tis a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way about to grapple with every
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184395:23"/> one of them ſingly, and by this means we find they multiply upon us: But this is to cut them off all at once, for make People but truly Moral Men, and then 'tis eaſy to make them Good and Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Let not therefore any of thoſe, who are the more immediate Undertakers of this Good Work, be diſcourag'd with any Oppoſition they meet with; they have but Two great Difficulties to ſtruggle with, and by the Bleſſing of God they will overcome them both; The <hi>Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> of good People, and the <hi>Fury</hi> of thoſe that are proſecuted.</p>
            <p>As for the Suſpicions and Jealouſies of good People, they will all wear off by degrees, when they conſider what have been already the good Effects of your Zeal for GOD &amp; Goodneſs. When they conſider that face of Piety and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion which of late is viſible in our Publick Worſhip in the Congregation; the great increaſe in the number of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants in all our Churches; the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Decreaſe of Publick and Scandalous Vice in this City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let them but lay theſe things, which are a ſubſtantial preſent advantage to our Church and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184395:23"/> Nation, againſt thoſe groundleſs ſurmiſes of ſome ill Conſequences they know not when, nor how. Let us but thorowly reform the Vices of this Age, and that is the ſureſt way of preventing ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences in the next. And indeed what Conſequences can be more formidable then that of open Curſing and Swearing, Adultery and Whoredom, and all that Impudent and Bare-fac'd Impiety which, with the Encouragement of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Contributions of good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they may be the happy means of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing.</p>
            <p>As to the other Difficulty you are to grapple with, you muſt expect the work will not be very eaſy; for the Rage and Fury of Perſons croſt and diſturb'd in their Vices, is very well likened by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to the fierceneſs of <hi>a Bear when ſhe is rob'd of her Whelps.</hi> But comfort your ſelves with this, that they have no other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt you, but what the Devils made to our Saviour, <hi>That you come to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them before their time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do you however appear as reſolute for the Cauſe of God, as they do for that of the Devil; The World is come to that paſs, that it is impoſſible to be truly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184395:24"/> Good without Courage and Reſolution. Let us but remain Undaunted, and this Impudent Impiety will looſe Ground dayly, till the Numbers of its Votaries grow ſo ſmall that they will be aſham'd of it. The worſt of Men have a ſecret Awe and Veneration for Vertue and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; there is ſo much of GOD in it, that they can no more raze out all Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for it in their Minds, then they can the Exiſtence of a Deity: And there is ſo much of the innate quality of the Devil in all Vice and Wickedneſs, that if we do reſiſt it manfully <hi>it will fly from us,</hi> and we ſhall ſurely be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors in the end.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
